<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DAEBFCG</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on DAEBFCG</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:14:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://daebfcg.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Headplate</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:14:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The headplate on this guitar will be 1/8 inch thick made up of two layers of 1/16 inch veneers - walnut with curly-maple on top. The first step is to slice out the veneers. The curly-maple is from the same board as the body of the guitar (recall the extra third section that was fortunately not needed) so should match nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-veneers-rough_hu_6fd88561df8cba39.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Rough cut veneer sheets for the headstock"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thickness-sanding"&gt;Thickness Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next they are sanded close to their final thickness on the spindle sander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are approximately 3/16 inch thick now but need to be 1/16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/thinning-before_hu_bf12eabb4adc5fa7.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Before thinning"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/spindle-sander_hu_640811fda7ec0d34.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Thinning veneer on the spindle sander"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will stop at around .070 or just a bit more than 1/16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/thinning-after_hu_3e0bb30e9a1cf4ee.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="After thinning"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thickness comes after some more sanding with a random orbit sander, and then hand sanding. To make this easier, I use double-sided tape to hold them down to a board that is clamped to the bench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/sanding_hu_39d585c67a4b00ae.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Hand sanding to final thickness"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After sanding, they total about 1/8 of an inch which is the target thickness of the headplate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/post-sanding_hu_8cbeeaa068c3c3ca.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Veneer pair sanded to overall final thickness"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bending"&gt;Bending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this guitar has a radiused end where the fretboard meets the headstock (Fender style) the headplate will be bent to accommodate this curve. The plates, even though only 1/16 inch thick, are not this flexible at all so will need to be heat-bent to shape first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is done by wetting the veneer with water and then bending over a hot pipe (around 350-400 degrees) to the necessary curve . Then they are held down to where they need to go to dry and cool using the spindle as a mold. This is basically the same way I bend hollowbody guitar sides, which I can hopefully cover in more detail in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/bending-drying_hu_b4356bee887bda59.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Headstock veneers cooling in the mold after bending"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now they are thicknessed and bent and ready to glue down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplates-pre-glue_hu_c91587f9611fdbf8.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Headstock veneers bent and ready to be attached"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gluing"&gt;Gluing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once correctly positioned, I use two small drill bits as index-pins in the waste areas to lock down the location and keep it from sliding around during gluing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-alignment_hu_ba8158342b44aa29.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Headplate veneer positioned and indexed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special top and bottom cauls and multiple clamps to apply pressure. Again, hot hide glue is used for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-gluing_hu_5aa968818e98cdc4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Gluing down a headplate veneer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The walnut layer glued down first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/walnut-layer-glued_hu_375573328ce42489.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Walnut veneer glued"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then then maple layer glued on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/maple-layer-glued_hu_5917d896b1250624.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Maple veneer glued"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="clean-up-and-trim"&gt;Clean up and trim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wrap up this stage, the overhang where the fretboard meets the headstock is trimmed back flush to the neck. This trimmed end will be covered by the end of the fretboard when it is attached later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-trimmed_hu_627dcc5451bba76d.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Trimming end of headplate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can see how the final shape of the headstock will be cut out (note light pencil lines) and where the holes for the tuners will go. I might make some final adjustments here, but this is pretty close to the final shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headstock-outlined_hu_e2fd7ec31314f42d.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Outline of headstock"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Electronics Plan V1</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511100736/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:36:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511100736/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some cold weather today so I am staying out of the shop and taking a closer look at the electronics planned for the guitar. Once the guitar is fully assembled and strung up for the first time (before finishing, though) I will see what it sounds like and test out different circuits and components using an external breadboard before drilling the final holes for the potentiometers (pots) and switches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="initial-idea"&gt;Initial Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511100736/electronics-layout-800_hu_54af2cadbaaf2c1a.jpg" width="800" height="772" alt="initial idea for electronics"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pickup-selector-toggle"&gt;Pickup Selector Toggle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a Les Paul style &lt;a href="https://www.stewmac.com/electronics/components-and-parts/switches/axlabs-3-way-6-pole-toggle-switch/"&gt;three-position toggle&lt;/a&gt; for the neck pickup, bridge pickup, or both in parallel. Black. I considered other options such as individual on/off switches for each pickup or a Telecaster-style blade pickup, but landed on the toggle with the idea that it is the most fool-proof way to easily flip while playing. The exact placement will be determined once I actually try to play the guitar to see where my hand goes when moving my elbow to get it in just the right spot. I will also angle switch movement so as not to make it &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; easy to flip to avoid accidentally switching it during vigorous strumming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck-and-bridge-tap-switches"&gt;Neck and Bridge Tap Switches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These will be &lt;a href="https://lovemyswitches.com/taiway-dpdt-on-on-switch-solder-lug-short-shaft-black-plated/"&gt;mini on/on toggle switches&lt;/a&gt; to control the pickup taps. The plan is to use &lt;a href="https://www.seymourduncan.com/single-product/quarter-pound-strat"&gt;Seymour Duncan Quarter Pound Strat&lt;/a&gt; Tapped pickups, which have a normal, modern high-output lead plus an additional tapped lead for a more vintage half-power output. This will allow the player to get two different sounds out of each pickup. I expect the normal (up) position will be more suitable for modern high-gain styles and the tapped (down) will produce more a traditional clean/jangly strat-type sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tone-bypass"&gt;Tone ByPass&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mini on/on toggle that will allow bypassing the tone circuit completely. When down, the normal tone and volume signal path is active. When switched up, the tone controls are bypassed and have no effect, so only the volume control is in the circuit. The thinking is that tone controls do attenuate the signal even when turned all the way up, because the resistance of the pots is not infinite and some signal is still getting grounded. Add in the capacitors, and there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; tone being changed even when the tone is on &amp;ldquo;10&amp;rdquo;. So this allows the player to get an even more pure and raw signal from the pickups without any influence by the tone controls. Only the volume control still works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tone-knob-1---bass-cut"&gt;Tone Knob 1 - Bass Cut&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit different from a normal single-tone control on a guitar. This guitar will have separate treble and bass controls (passive). This is directly copying the G&amp;amp;L S500 wiring. Most guitars just have a single tone control which attenuates the high frequencies. Here with the additional bass-frequency attenuation, the player will be able to clean up the signal to cut through a mix better by cutting out some bass. This will be a 1MG Ohm audio taper pot, with a small capacitor around 1000 picofarads. When testing the circuit I will determine the best capacitor value. Black, &lt;a href="https://lovemyswitches.com/anodized-aluminum-knob-the-hi-fi-1-4-smooth-shaft-20mm-od/"&gt;20mm aluminum knobs&lt;/a&gt; for the tone controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tone-knob-2---treble-cut"&gt;Tone Knob 2 - Treble Cut&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the more traditional tone control that just cuts the high end. I am thinking 500k audio-taper pot, with a .022 microfarad capacitor. Again, will experiment to find a good sounding capacitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="volume"&gt;Volume&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic volume control. 250k linear pot. I prefer linear pots for volume, as opposed to audio-taper. Note the large knob&amp;hellip; I am thinking of using &lt;a href="https://lovemyswitches.com/solid-aluminum-knob-mission-control-1-4-smooth-shaft-32mm-od/"&gt;freakishly large 32mm knob&lt;/a&gt; for the volume to allow the player to easily grab it with their pinky finger while playing to do dramatic volume swells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="direct-out"&gt;Direct Out&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last on/on toggle switch near the volume, which will bypass both the volume and tone from the circuit and send the pickup signal directly to the jack. This is for an even more pure, raw signal unaffected by any pots or capacitors. This can act as a mini &amp;ldquo;boost&amp;rdquo; effect during a performance. Used this way, it is sometimes called a blower switch. It might also be useful for recording, where all tone and volume is controlled during mixing and you want the purest and loudest signal to be recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="jack"&gt;Jack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thinking of trying one of these &lt;a href="https://www.amplifiedparts.com/products/jack-pure-tone-mono-open-circuit"&gt;PureTone&lt;/a&gt; jacks. In black of course to match all the other hardware. The jack will be in the side of guitar, Telecaster style, using a nice &lt;a href="https://www.stewmac.com/parts-and-hardware/jack-plates/electrosocket-jack-mount/"&gt;recessed plate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="breadboarding"&gt;Breadboarding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I usually do is mount the pickups into the guitar and connect the leads to a breadboard tester on my desk, which is then connected to an amp. The allows me to fiddle around with different components and wiring schemes before soldering anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More photos and updates to come on this subject.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Body Top and Back Plates</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 16:47:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Before slicing out a headplate veneer from the curly maple, I decided to make sure I have the body sections successfully roughed out. Here is the cherry and maple stock for the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/body-stock_hu_d401e390c042bee3.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="body stock"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maple piece should have enough length for three sections, although I only need two for the left and right &amp;ldquo;wings&amp;rdquo; of the body. Instead of making two generous sections, I decided to try to get three out of it to have an extra in case of mistakes. This requires careful planning of the sections. The acrylic template is used to layout the sections to be cut. This is one of the more critical things to get right because this curly maple is a pretty special board and I do not want to screw it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/layout1_hu_1a239240aa8ab96c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="maple board layout"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/layout2_hu_506a2f8ec09a8aa2.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="maple board layout wings"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="resawing"&gt;Resawing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maple is 3/4 thick and each section will be sliced to get two approximately 3/8 inch thick slices for the top and back. This is one the more challenging and nerve-wracking parts of the build, as it is pushing my little bandsaw to the limit. The 4.75 inch width is in fact the maximum height of cut the saw can do. An unsteady hand or the cut drifting off track and board would be ruined. Thankfully I have a new 1/2 inch WoodSlicer blade and it chugs through the 4.75 inch maple with no trouble at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/resaw1_hu_4150b114f9f6a0ed.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="resawing maple 1"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/resaw2_hu_327a382ed044a10b.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="resawing maple 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always nice to see the bookmatched slices for the first time coming off the saw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/bookmatch1_hu_623c00dac426117c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="bookmatching 1"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/bookmatch2_hu_2302a5060bdc30f8.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="bookmatching 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a little annoyed that I did not plan for bookmatching the plates side by side on the finished guitar. But due to the fact the the left and right wings are different lengths, it would have meant resawing the entire board first which I am not sure I could have done. Instead, each bookmatched pair will be a top and back of a wing. I am not too worried about it though. It should still look great. The tiger-stripe figure should really pop once it is sanded smooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511091047/maple-wings_hu_577a5d1b931382ad.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="maple body wings rough cut"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cherry board will yield the inner body sections that will be sandwiched between the maple plates. I will cut out the cherry sections later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this was a success, I can now use the remaining third section of maple to get my headplate veneer slice and return focus to the headstock.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Headstock Profile</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 19:09:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this step, the headstock is taken down to the final thickness according the the side profile of the template. The bottom needs to be one inch down from the top face of the neck surface, and the top face cut down to the final thickness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/headstock-raw_hu_726ba7c33e807076.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="headstock rough"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the bottom is cut back on the bandsaw. This is followed up by planing it flat using the Safe-T-Planer on the drill press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/headstock-back-cut_hu_6ee44e6143a2de5f.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="headstock back cut"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/safetplaner_hu_425f3f1e5b788e8.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="safe-t-planer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top face is also cut back on the bandsaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/bandsaw_hu_b078d0e1ea862356.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="cutting the top face on the bandsaw"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the spindle sander with a 3 inch spindle and a fence is used to take it down to the final thickness and also add the radiused corner where the fretboard end meets the headstock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/spindle-sander_hu_a289ef76bfb5bda.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="spindle sander"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thickness needs to be 9/16 inch for the tuning machines to fit nicely. However, since I will be adding a headplate which will add 1/8 inch to the thickness, I need to take the headstock down to 7/16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/final-profile_hu_ed7f35ba33a283a2.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="final headstoock profile"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some final sanding by hand. Here the spindle-on-a-dowel trick is being employed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/hand-sanding_hu_32ae37d7e47acb01.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="final sanding by hand"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511081309/final-profile-2_hu_e5b82e9b5787d2a4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="final headstoock profile sanded"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ready for the headplate veneers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Headstock Ears</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511072359/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:19:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511072359/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Time to add the ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the headstock template is wider than the neck, so some wood will need to be added to the sides to accommodate the extra width. The technical term for these additional pieces of wood is the &amp;ldquo;ears&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511072359/headstock1_hu_61a27e4d0f19ee0a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="headstock before"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately there is some excess wood at the end which will fit nicely and also match in appearance. Just need to cut those out, flip around, and glue into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511072359/headstock_glued_hu_76f1761ef3453193.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="headstock glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there is enough width to cut out the headstock shape. I will now be working on getting the headstock mostly done, since trying to do this once the body is attached would be awkward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511072359/headstock2_hu_4d6b3d4a73cdd58d.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="headstock after"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Truss Rod Channels</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:27:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Now that the neck/body core is glued up and planed flat, it is time to determine the layout. The templates come in handy here to see where the body, neck, and headstock should land. The key points to mark are the zero-fret, 24-fret, and bridge locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/core_layout_hu_c07e1e9d8f38c263.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Core body layout"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to have the truss rod adjustment at the body end of the neck, as opposed to in the headstock. I think this will make the neck to headstock area more structurally sound since less wood will need to be removed. Plus I think it will look better with the headplate overlay scheme I have in mind. Also, I think it might make adjustment easier with strings on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_adjust_detail_hu_1d3178c35a2eab7e.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod adjustment plan"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truss rod adjustment nut will be hidden under the end of the fretboard and will be accessible by removing a small plate made of either wood or brass that sits between the fretboard end and the neck pickup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the allen wrench in, I am drilling out a little round area just large enough to get the wrench in. This will be covered up so will not normally be visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This round area is drilled out with a forstener bit, and also makes a good place to start the channel route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note - the previous photos show the headstock end on the left side, but in the remaining photos the neck core is flipped around with the body end on the left and headstock on the right (for easier routing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_channel_hu_c8af7169a0f7bc7a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod Channel routed"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_installed_hu_39ee89e4021ddef4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod Installed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to a two-way adjustable truss rod, I am also adding two 1/8 x 1/4 carbon fiber bars for extra stiffening. A stiff neck is a good thing! I am placing the carbon fiber bars into the same center piece of wood that the truss rod goes in. My thinking is that when the rod is adjusted the flexing will primarily be in the center piece of wood and pull the side pieces along with it. Alternatively, if the carbon fiber bars were in the side pieces instead, the sides would have extra resistance to flexing when the center piece is flexed and would stress the glue joint more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_and_bars_hu_92f3b9b6afd4b014.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod and Carbon Fiber Bars"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pinpoint location bit is great for getting the router adjusted perfectly centered along the line I want to route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/router_pinpoint_hu_812bae9b206dff96.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Router pinpoint bit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truss rod and carbon fiber bars installed. The carbon fiber bars can now be glued in. The truss rod will be removed for now installed permanently later right before the fretboard is glued down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_bars_installed_hu_bbeff3ddbf36916d.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod and Carbon Fiber Bars Installed"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laminating the Neck</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:52:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-blanks-2_hu_c9621be59526cf79.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck blanks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am hand-jointing everything with a #7 plane. Would I like to have a jointer? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The #7 plane is a little more work, but when properly honed and used it leaves the surface &lt;strong&gt;dead flat&lt;/strong&gt; and very smooth. It should make for some very tight joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-blanks-1_hu_7932d6b77dd7146c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck blanks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use hot hide glue exclusively. More on this topic later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-glued_hu_af69a8c12d764102.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two screws are used to keep the pieces in place while gluing. They are strategically placed so the hole will be covered up by another part later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-rough_hu_f609c864e43c314e.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Rough neck glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to show you what this thing is and how it fits into the overall build, here is the simulated drawing of the full neck-through guitar. This makes up the &amp;ldquo;core&amp;rdquo; of the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/drawing_hu_91563aa3cfc87e0b.jpg" width="261" height="800" alt="Neck-through drawing"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The core extends all the way up through the headstock, but it is covered up in this drawing.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Body Templates</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 13:16:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-cutout_hu_598eb23edf4e5db0.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Template cut out"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to make a full-size cardstock template of the body first. This helps with wood stock selection and cutting. Since this is a solidbody, I will be routing the edges to the final shape, so will also need a routing template. The routing template will be made from 1/4 inch thick clear acrylic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Libre Office Draw and it has poor tiling capabilities. So I need to use the following trick to print anything larger than 8.5 x 11. First export the full size drawing as an SVG file. This will be the full 40 x 20 inches or whatever. Then place the SVG on a new 8.5 x 11 document. Get it back to 100% size and crop to fit on the page. Move the SVG around and adjust the crop to manually tile and print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-tiles_hu_1e298e80ff253569.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Template Tiles"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to make the routing template, I transfered the cardstock template onto some Ramboard I had leftover from the my kitchen floor project. This stuff is great for other uses like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I used spray adhesive to attach it to the 12 x 16 acrylic sheet. Got two of these from amazon for about $15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-1_hu_a0a3309df21539d4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I rough cut it out on the bandsaw, and used my spindle sander to get it to the final shape. A little hand sanding with 240, and it is good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-2_hu_1a92a4eb2b8e7b57.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture shows it still with the protective layer still attached. It will be much nicer and clear when that is removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-3_hu_6dac6a0c2037a41b.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 3"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wood Selection</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 12:49:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/woodstack_hu_66cd560f6ec8b00b.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Woodstack"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will be another &amp;ldquo;Local Woods&amp;rdquo; guitar with all species of wood used being native to North America, and some locally harvested from Alabama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck--cental-core"&gt;Neck / Cental Core&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thee-ply laminate (vertical) of Cherry / Walnut / Cherry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/black-cherry/"&gt;Prunus serotina&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnut &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/black-walnut/"&gt;Juglans nigra&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body"&gt;Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another three-ply laminate (horizontal) of Curly Maple, Cherry, and Curly Maple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curly Maple &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/curly-maple/"&gt;Acer sp.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure the exact species of the piece that I have but I suspect it is Big Leaf &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/bigleaf-maple/"&gt;Acer macrophyllum&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fretboard"&gt;Fretboard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still have not fully committed yet. I am thinking Walnut, but also considering using the last piece of Persimmon that I have. The Walnut will look good being dark, but I am concerned about the long term durability. The Persimmon will be much harder and more durable. It is in fact the only native north American tree of the Ebony family. However it is more of a light tan gray color which I am not sure will look good against the maple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persimmon &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/persimmon/"&gt;Diospyros virginiana&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="headplate"&gt;Headplate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top layer of Curly Maple with a slice of Walnut sandwiched between. You will see what I mean&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a lot fewer choices to make compared to a hollowbody guitar that has a lot more parts (braces, linings, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Initial Conception and Design</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 21:39:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="new-solid-body-electric-guitar-project"&gt;New solid-body electric guitar project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my next guitar project I&amp;rsquo;ll be building a solid-body electric guitar from scratch. The inspiration for the design comes partly from the Alembic Further guitar with a neck-through design and curly maple top and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m building off this basic Strat type guitar design with a couple of customizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/ElectricGuitar_hu_21a6d84361bad184.jpg" width="253" height="800" alt="Plans"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="multi-scale"&gt;Multi Scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost is the multi-scale. It will be 25.5&amp;quot; on the bass side, and 25&amp;quot; on the treble. This is to retain the rich overtones on the bass notes (i.e. more Fenderish twang), while fattening up the high end with a little less overtone and more fundamental (i.e. getting in to Les Paul territory, but not quite.) The 25.5&amp;quot; is typical Fender strat, and the 25 is used on PRS and Danelectro guitars. I could have gone shorter on the treble to get even more fatter/sweeter sound there, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been liking the feel of the slightly longer scale lengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck-through"&gt;Neck Through&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always said if I build a solid body, it will be a neck through. It just seems to make sense structurally for good sound coupling. Hopefully it will give it some extra sustain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="two-pickups"&gt;Two Pickups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; pickup. The plan is to use 2 Seymour Duncan Quarter Pound Strat pickups, mounted directly to the body. No pickguard. (More detail on the electronics coming up later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body-shape"&gt;Body Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is based loosely on a strat, but is more in the 80&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;super strat&amp;rdquo; vein with sharper horns. I&amp;rsquo;ve also narrowed the mid-section a bit, inspired by the early 70&amp;rsquo;s Kay strat knockoff guitars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="chambered-body"&gt;Chambered Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it won&amp;rsquo;t actually be a fully solid body. To cut down on weight, as well as give some extra airy resonance, the body will have 2 large empty chambers. The chamber on the right side will conveniently house the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="plans"&gt;Plans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my guitar builds, I first start with a full-size drawing using Libre Office Draw. From this, I print out cardstock templates.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>