<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DAEBFCG</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on DAEBFCG</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:52:18 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://daebfcg.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Laminating the Neck</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:52:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-blanks-2_hu_c9621be59526cf79.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck blanks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am hand-jointing everything with a #7 plane. Would I like to have a jointer? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The #7 plane is a little more work, but when properly honed and used it leaves the surface &lt;strong&gt;dead flat&lt;/strong&gt; and very smooth. It should make for some very tight joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-blanks-1_hu_7932d6b77dd7146c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck blanks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use hot hide glue exclusively. More on this topic later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-glued_hu_af69a8c12d764102.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two screws are used to keep the pieces in place while gluing. They are strategically placed so the hole will be covered up by another part later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-rough_hu_f609c864e43c314e.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Rough neck glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to show you what this thing is and how it fits into the overall build, here is the simulated drawing of the full neck-through guitar. This makes up the &amp;ldquo;core&amp;rdquo; of the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/drawing_hu_91563aa3cfc87e0b.jpg" width="261" height="800" alt="Neck-through drawing"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The core extends all the way up through the headstock, but it is covered up in this drawing.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Body Templates</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 13:16:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-cutout_hu_598eb23edf4e5db0.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Template cut out"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to make a full-size cardstock template of the body first. This helps with wood stock selection and cutting. Since this is a solidbody, I will be routing the edges to the final shape, so will also need a routing template. The routing template will be made from 1/4 inch thick clear acrylic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Libre Office Draw and it has poor tiling capabilities. So I need to use the following trick to print anything larger than 8.5 x 11. First export the full size drawing as an SVG file. This will be the full 40 x 20 inches or whatever. Then place the SVG on a new 8.5 x 11 document. Get it back to 100% size and crop to fit on the page. Move the SVG around and adjust the crop to manually tile and print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-tiles_hu_1e298e80ff253569.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Template Tiles"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to make the routing template, I transfered the cardstock template onto some Ramboard I had leftover from the my kitchen floor project. This stuff is great for other uses like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I used spray adhesive to attach it to the 12 x 16 acrylic sheet. Got two of these from amazon for about $15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-1_hu_a0a3309df21539d4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I rough cut it out on the bandsaw, and used my spindle sander to get it to the final shape. A little hand sanding with 240, and it is good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-2_hu_1a92a4eb2b8e7b57.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture shows it still with the protective layer still attached. It will be much nicer and clear when that is removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-3_hu_6dac6a0c2037a41b.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 3"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wood Selection</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 12:49:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This will be another &amp;ldquo;Local Woods&amp;rdquo; guitar with all species of wood used being native to North America, and some locally harvested from Alabama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck--cental-core"&gt;Neck / Cental Core&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thee-ply laminate (vertical) of Cherry / Walnut / Cherry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/black-cherry/"&gt;Prunus serotina&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnut &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/black-walnut/"&gt;Juglans nigra&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body"&gt;Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another three-ply laminate (horizontal) of Curly Maple, Cherry, and Curly Maple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curly Maple &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/curly-maple/"&gt;Acer sp.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure the exact species of the piece that I have but I suspect it is Big Leaf &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/bigleaf-maple/"&gt;Acer macrophyllum&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fretboard"&gt;Fretboard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still have not fully committed yet. I am thinking Walnut, but also considering using the last piece of Persimmon that I have. The Walnut will look good being dark, but I am concerned about the long term durability. The Persimmon will be much harder and more durable. It is in fact the only native north American tree of the Ebony family. However it is more of a light tan gray color which I am not sure will look good against the maple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persimmon &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/persimmon/"&gt;Diospyros virginiana&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="headplate"&gt;Headplate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top layer of Curly Maple with a slice of Walnut sandwiched between. You will see what I mean&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a lot fewer choices to make compared to a hollowbody guitar that has a lot more parts (braces, linings, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Initial Conception and Design</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 21:39:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="new-solid-body-electric-guitar-project"&gt;New solid-body electric guitar project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my next guitar project I&amp;rsquo;ll be building a solid-body electric guitar from scratch. The inspiration for the design comes partly from the Alembic Further guitar with a neck-through design and curly maple top and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m building off this basic Strat type guitar design with a couple of customizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/ElectricGuitar_hu_21a6d84361bad184.jpg" width="253" height="800" alt="Plans"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="multi-scale"&gt;Multi Scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost is the multi-scale. It will be 25.5&amp;quot; on the bass side, and 25&amp;quot; on the treble. This is to retain the rich overtones on the bass notes (i.e. more Fenderish twang), while fattening up the high end with a little less overtone and more fundamental (i.e. getting in to Les Paul territory, but not quite.) The 25.5&amp;quot; is typical Fender strat, and the 25 is used on PRS and Danelectro guitars. I could have gone shorter on the treble to get even more fatter/sweeter sound there, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been liking the feel of the slightly longer scale lengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck-through"&gt;Neck Through&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always said if I build a solid body, it will be a neck through. It just seems to make sense structurally for good sound coupling. Hopefully it will give it some extra sustain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="two-pickups"&gt;Two Pickups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; pickup. The plan is to use 2 Seymour Duncan Quarter Pound Strat pickups, mounted directly to the body. No pickguard. (More detail on the electronics coming up later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body-shape"&gt;Body Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is based loosely on a strat, but is more in the 80&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;super strat&amp;rdquo; vein with sharper horns. I&amp;rsquo;ve also narrowed the mid-section a bit, inspired by the early 70&amp;rsquo;s Kay strat knockoff guitars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="chambered-body"&gt;Chambered Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it won&amp;rsquo;t actually be a fully solid body. To cut down on weight, as well as give some extra airy resonance, the body will have 2 large empty chambers. The chamber on the right side will conveniently house the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="plans"&gt;Plans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my guitar builds, I first start with a full-size drawing using Libre Office Draw. From this, I print out cardstock templates.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/about/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Journal of luthiery and musical projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>