<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on DAEBFCG</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on DAEBFCG</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:19:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Truss Rod Channels</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:27:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Now that the neck/body core is glued up and planed flat, it is time to determine the layout. The templates come in handy here to see where the body, neck, and headstock should land. The key points to mark are the zero-fret, 24-fret, and bridge locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/core_layout_hu_c07e1e9d8f38c263.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Core body layout"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to have the truss rod adjustment at the body end of the neck, as opposed to in the headstock. I think this will make the neck to headstock area more structurally sound since less wood will need to be removed. Plus I think it will look better with the headplate overlay scheme I have in mind. Also, I think it might make adjustment easier with strings on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_adjust_detail_hu_1d3178c35a2eab7e.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod adjustment plan"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truss rod adjustment nut will be hidden under the end of the fretboard and will be accessible by removing a small plate made of either wood or brass that sits between the fretboard end and the neck pickup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the allen wrench in, I am drilling out a little round area just large enough to get the wrench in. This will be covered up so will not normally be visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This round area is drilled out with a forstener bit, and also makes a good place to start the channel route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note - the previous photos show the headstock end on the left side, but in the remaining photos the neck core is flipped around with the body end on the left and headstock on the right (for easier routing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_channel_hu_c8af7169a0f7bc7a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod Channel routed"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_installed_hu_39ee89e4021ddef4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod Installed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to a two-way adjustable truss rod, I am also adding two 1/8 x 1/4 carbon fiber bars for extra stiffening. A stiff neck is a good thing! I am placing the carbon fiber bars into the same center piece of wood that the truss rod goes in. My thinking is that when the rod is adjusted the flexing will primarily be in the center piece of wood and pull the side pieces along with it. Alternatively, if the carbon fiber bars were in the side pieces instead, the sides would have extra resistance to flexing when the center piece is flexed and would stress the glue joint more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_and_bars_hu_92f3b9b6afd4b014.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod and Carbon Fiber Bars"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pinpoint location bit is great for getting the router adjusted perfectly centered along the line I want to route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/router_pinpoint_hu_812bae9b206dff96.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Router pinpoint bit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truss rod and carbon fiber bars installed. The carbon fiber bars can now be glued in. The truss rod will be removed for now installed permanently later right before the fretboard is glued down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511070827/truss_rod_bars_installed_hu_bbeff3ddbf36916d.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Truss Rod and Carbon Fiber Bars Installed"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laminating the Neck</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:52:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-blanks-2_hu_c9621be59526cf79.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck blanks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am hand-jointing everything with a #7 plane. Would I like to have a jointer? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The #7 plane is a little more work, but when properly honed and used it leaves the surface &lt;strong&gt;dead flat&lt;/strong&gt; and very smooth. It should make for some very tight joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-blanks-1_hu_7932d6b77dd7146c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck blanks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use hot hide glue exclusively. More on this topic later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-glued_hu_af69a8c12d764102.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Neck glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two screws are used to keep the pieces in place while gluing. They are strategically placed so the hole will be covered up by another part later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/neck-rough_hu_f609c864e43c314e.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Rough neck glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to show you what this thing is and how it fits into the overall build, here is the simulated drawing of the full neck-through guitar. This makes up the &amp;ldquo;core&amp;rdquo; of the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251104/drawing_hu_91563aa3cfc87e0b.jpg" width="261" height="800" alt="Neck-through drawing"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The core extends all the way up through the headstock, but it is covered up in this drawing.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Body Templates</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 13:16:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-cutout_hu_598eb23edf4e5db0.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Template cut out"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to make a full-size cardstock template of the body first. This helps with wood stock selection and cutting. Since this is a solidbody, I will be routing the edges to the final shape, so will also need a routing template. The routing template will be made from 1/4 inch thick clear acrylic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Libre Office Draw and it has poor tiling capabilities. So I need to use the following trick to print anything larger than 8.5 x 11. First export the full size drawing as an SVG file. This will be the full 40 x 20 inches or whatever. Then place the SVG on a new 8.5 x 11 document. Get it back to 100% size and crop to fit on the page. Move the SVG around and adjust the crop to manually tile and print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-tiles_hu_1e298e80ff253569.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Template Tiles"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to make the routing template, I transfered the cardstock template onto some Ramboard I had leftover from the my kitchen floor project. This stuff is great for other uses like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I used spray adhesive to attach it to the 12 x 16 acrylic sheet. Got two of these from amazon for about $15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-1_hu_a0a3309df21539d4.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I rough cut it out on the bandsaw, and used my spindle sander to get it to the final shape. A little hand sanding with 240, and it is good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-2_hu_1a92a4eb2b8e7b57.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture shows it still with the protective layer still attached. It will be much nicer and clear when that is removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251101/template-acrylic-3_hu_6dac6a0c2037a41b.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Acrylic routing template 3"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wood Selection</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 12:49:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251011/woodstack_hu_66cd560f6ec8b00b.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Woodstack"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will be another &amp;ldquo;Local Woods&amp;rdquo; guitar with all species of wood used being native to North America, and some locally harvested from Alabama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck--cental-core"&gt;Neck / Cental Core&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thee-ply laminate (vertical) of Cherry / Walnut / Cherry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/black-cherry/"&gt;Prunus serotina&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnut &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/black-walnut/"&gt;Juglans nigra&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body"&gt;Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another three-ply laminate (horizontal) of Curly Maple, Cherry, and Curly Maple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curly Maple &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/curly-maple/"&gt;Acer sp.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure the exact species of the piece that I have but I suspect it is Big Leaf &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/bigleaf-maple/"&gt;Acer macrophyllum&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fretboard"&gt;Fretboard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still have not fully committed yet. I am thinking Walnut, but also considering using the last piece of Persimmon that I have. The Walnut will look good being dark, but I am concerned about the long term durability. The Persimmon will be much harder and more durable. It is in fact the only native north American tree of the Ebony family. However it is more of a light tan gray color which I am not sure will look good against the maple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persimmon &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.wood-database.com/persimmon/"&gt;Diospyros virginiana&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="headplate"&gt;Headplate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top layer of Curly Maple with a slice of Walnut sandwiched between. You will see what I mean&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a lot fewer choices to make compared to a hollowbody guitar that has a lot more parts (braces, linings, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Initial Conception and Design</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 21:39:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="new-solid-body-electric-guitar-project"&gt;New solid-body electric guitar project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my next guitar project I&amp;rsquo;ll be building a solid-body electric guitar from scratch. The inspiration for the design comes partly from the Alembic Further guitar with a neck-through design and curly maple top and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m building off this basic Strat type guitar design with a couple of customizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/ElectricGuitar_hu_21a6d84361bad184.jpg" width="253" height="800" alt="Plans"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="multi-scale"&gt;Multi Scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost is the multi-scale. It will be 25.5&amp;quot; on the bass side, and 25&amp;quot; on the treble. This is to retain the rich overtones on the bass notes (i.e. more Fenderish twang), while fattening up the high end with a little less overtone and more fundamental (i.e. getting in to Les Paul territory, but not quite.) The 25.5&amp;quot; is typical Fender strat, and the 25 is used on PRS and Danelectro guitars. I could have gone shorter on the treble to get even more fatter/sweeter sound there, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been liking the feel of the slightly longer scale lengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck-through"&gt;Neck Through&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always said if I build a solid body, it will be a neck through. It just seems to make sense structurally for good sound coupling. Hopefully it will give it some extra sustain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="two-pickups"&gt;Two Pickups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; pickup. The plan is to use 2 Seymour Duncan Quarter Pound Strat pickups, mounted directly to the body. No pickguard. (More detail on the electronics coming up later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body-shape"&gt;Body Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is based loosely on a strat, but is more in the 80&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;super strat&amp;rdquo; vein with sharper horns. I&amp;rsquo;ve also narrowed the mid-section a bit, inspired by the early 70&amp;rsquo;s Kay strat knockoff guitars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="chambered-body"&gt;Chambered Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it won&amp;rsquo;t actually be a fully solid body. To cut down on weight, as well as give some extra airy resonance, the body will have 2 large empty chambers. The chamber on the right side will conveniently house the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="plans"&gt;Plans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my guitar builds, I first start with a full-size drawing using Libre Office Draw. From this, I print out cardstock templates.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Super K</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 16:51:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;strong&gt;Super K&lt;/strong&gt;, a guitar I completed in the Spring of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/super_k_hu_b0b916348c671269.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inspiration for this comes from a early 1960s Kay Value Leader guitar that I own, which is one of my favorites. It has a great jazz sound. The construction is interesting too. It is semi-hollow with just a single block of wood (spruce?) that runs parallel to the bridge from side to side. Otherwise hollow. This gives it a little more acoustic volume that a typical electric, and I play it unplugged most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My version, The Super K, is constructed the same way, and has the same 24 1/4 inch scale length. I used nicer woods and a much hotter pickup though. I think it sounds even better than the Value Leader!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/side_2_hu_e2cc504af81fd0da.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K side"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/neck_hu_f6ba7df6590274b0.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K neck"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body shape is roughly based on the Kay Thin Twin Jimmy Reed guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="electronics"&gt;Electronics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First knob - Volume. This is a push-pull switch. Down is normal master volume. Up bypasses the tone circuit and piezo pickup, for just the Phat cat alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second knob - Tone. Also a push-pull. Down is a 0.015 μF capacitor. Up is a 0.005 μF capacitor. The .005 really adds more midrange for a more forceful sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third knob - Piezo Blend. This acts as a volume for the piezo pickup only. It is a push-pull too, and when pulled up turns off the piezo altogether for just the magnetic pickup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/side_hu_54a736cfb3620b05.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K side view"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/back_hu_45aadfcd58634e2c.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K back"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/back_open_hu_7d3edaa29169bdf3.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K back controls"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/fretboard_hu_3535973fcccb3078.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Super K fretboard"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="construction-photos"&gt;Construction Photos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the secret of the horizontal sound block is revealed. I put my custom spin on it, by notching out the ends. The though is that a little less mass towards the edge will help the top resonate more, possibly. I did not need to angle it so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/inside_hu_80e0d6f1d903e385.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Super K inside"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/inside_front_hu_16572e77f6e72a80.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Super K inside front"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/inside_block_hu_66449822dcf2ffa5.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Super K inside sound block"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/neck_construction_hu_51a98f295ab82605.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Super K neck construction"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20250704/neck_gluing_hu_92fc72b8f7023620.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Super K neck glue up"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="specs"&gt;Specs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale Length: 24.25&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top: Solid Sitka Spruce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back and Sides: Walnut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neck: Cherry (three ply)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fretboard: Persimmon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bridge: Persimmon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tailpiece: Walnut/Persimmon/Cherry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headplate: Maple/Walnut/Persimmon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bindings: Curly Maple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headblock: Spruce / Walnut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tailblock: Basswood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internal Linings: Basswood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Center Sound Block: Sitka Spruce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pickup Ring: Persimmon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control Plate Cover: Maple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frets: 55x105 (extra jumbo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pickup: Seymour Duncan Phat Cat, plus a piezo rod under the bridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuners: Sperzel USA Trim-Lock, Chrome, #3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strings: Optima Gold 11-52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: Platina shellac, French polished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One odd thing about this guitar is that it has no sound holes. I copied the Value Leader in this respect. However, I found is sounds quite a bit better (clearer mids) with the back control plate removed. It must need &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; sound hole for good Helmoltz resonance. The next one will have side sound ports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would like to make my own wood knobs someday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Nandina</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 20:08:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For my first full size guitar project, I decided to tackle a multi-scale archtop guitar. This was started in 2019, and after fits and starts was finally playable by the Spring of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call it a &amp;ldquo;prototype&amp;rdquo; because it was truly an experiment. The name comes from an invasive shrub that grows all around our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here it is in the rough - unfinished and strung up for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/nandina_hu_14c7c73e190a07f.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Nandina rough"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="some-notable-features-of-this-guitar"&gt;Some notable features of this guitar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-Scale. 25.5 inches bass side, 24 inches treble side, with the 7th fret perpendicular.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douglas Fir top, made from a 4x4 post from Home Depot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry back, sides, and neck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persimmon fretboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nandina&amp;rdquo; leaf soundholes in the top and side ports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jasper dot inlays. These ended up looking cool on the Persimmon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headstock shape of my own design, descended what I used on my cigar box guitars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="build-process"&gt;Build process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loosely followed the Benedetto method for construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major screw-up occurred when I was carving the back plate arch. As per the methodology, a drill press is used to drill progressively deeper holes into the 1 inch thick plate to form the graduated arch before actually carving. While doing so, the depth stop on my drill press slipped and I drilled holes all the way through. So I had to plug these holes and accept the cosmetic flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-back_hu_ce95b5476cc80f9a.jpg" width="800" height="450" alt="Nandina back"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="construction-photos"&gt;Construction Photos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-body-parts_hu_b8aa60ae70ecb3c2.jpg" width="800" height="450" alt="Nandina parts"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-body_sideport_hu_434bd8d1138a70a6.jpg" width="800" height="450" alt="Nandina sides"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-inside_hu_805837594153ee04.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="Nandina body inside"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Solid Spruce linings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="top"&gt;Top&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top plate was created from joining multiple sections of quarter sawn Douglas Fir boards from the post from Home Depot. This actually worked out pretty well. The glue joints blend in well with the quarter-sawn grain lines, so are not too visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Douglas Fir actually seems like really good wood for guitar tops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-pieces_hu_b05ca09593f489b1.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="top pieces"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-top_hu_3cc35f52200aa221.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="top cut out"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="bracing"&gt;Bracing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to keep it fairly minimal. X-braced. It seems to have worked out well.
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20240420/archtop-top-braces_hu_6bc0ff1aa44dfde1.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="braces"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guitar is currently out under the care of Greg. I will post more pics of the finished guitar with the electronics installed, knobs on, and French Polish finish applied, at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>