<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on DAEBFCG</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on DAEBFCG</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>/posts</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:16:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Body: Inner Layer</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:16:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The body of this guitar will be comprised of three layers of hardwood - an inner core of cherry sandwiched between two outer layers of maple. The maple outer sections have already been prepared so now the focus is on the inner cherry layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_woods_hu_b909ffb29b4a6b99.png" width="600" height="446" alt="Sketch of the body layers"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While preparing the cherry board to be a guitar body, I had to change my approach and do quite a bit extra work to get the wood parts into what I consider a suitable state for an instrument. What follows is the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, here was the rough board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/cherry_board_rough_hu_a7857d87b840d296.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Rough cherry board to be used the inner body layer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was some end-checking and cup-warping. This is a very old board. Old wood is good, right? In my optimism, I believed I could work around these defects. The cupping should have been a red flag&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After much planing to remove the cup-warp the board was nice and flat and in good shape to be cut out into the two sides for the guitar body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/cherry_board_planed_hu_8ee4d7ecd7ab8375.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Cherry board planed flat"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/cherry_board_body_1_hu_41cde574536cb73a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Planning how the body sections will be cut from the board"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="then-i-noticed-something"&gt;then I noticed something&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/cherry_board_end_hu_fdd05ecb5761a080.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="End of cherry showing tangential grain"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This board is very flat-sawn, and also has a considerable amount of sap wood (the light area) compared to the heart wood. This explains why it cupped over the years. I was very worried that this grain direction and mix of sap and heartwood would be cause for instability in the finished instrument, causing warping, tuning problems, uneven shrinkage, and eventually cracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, quarter sawn wood is used, where the grain runs vertically instead of side to side like in this flat sawn board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Waiting for another, more quarter sawn, cherry board this wide to come along would delay this project for years probably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-plan"&gt;New Plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to turn a flat sawn board into quarter sawn? Cut into strips, turn them 90 degrees, glue together. This will result in a much more stable structure. The downside is it is a lot more work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there was enough wood in the board to achieve this. To make the guitar shape, not every section needs to be the full length, so some parts of the board can become two or three sections. I planned out the sections on the computer, lettered each section A-N, cut them out, and started the long process of gluing them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_sections_plan_hu_38cff35178a7286a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Plan of how to get the required sections"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_sections_strips_hu_3acab5d15a16a682.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="The cherry board cut into strips to be glued up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all the strips are cut out, I arranged them according to the body template to get the final plan for joining them together. One good thing is that since the board was already planed flat, the faces to be glues are already mating nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_sections_laidout_hu_384b918691b7d653.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Checking that the sections will form the correct shape"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the innermost strips are maple. This was somewhat unplanned, but the maple top and back pieces are just shy of the necessary width, so I plan to have some narrow strips on the inside to widen the neck area just a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for the glueing process, which I did over the course of a few weeks, taking advantage of dry weather when it came. This did require getting some larger clamps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_sections_gluing_hu_9fff1bbc6044efc5.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Gluing up the sections one by one to form the body inner layer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some more gluing and planing, the resulting halves are complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_inner_layers_hu_808ae04b40bf851d.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="The completed halves of the inner body layer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also ended up using some strips of walnut on the inside to compensate for lost width due to all the cutting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202602190716/body_inner_layer_with_template_hu_a74f7ccb479501b.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="The completed halves of the inner body layer shown with the body template"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step will be to cut out the chambers for the electronics and weight reduction, then glue on the top and back maple plates, and finally attach the halves to the neck core to form the final body.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Headstock Shaping Part 2</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601161647/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 22:48:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601161647/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Now that I have test-fit the tuners, the headstock can be shaped into the final form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601161647/headstock_1_hu_d4fbbaf0a5a8fe06.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Headstock shaped to the final form"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This just required a little work on the disc sander to get the sides flat and converging to the end. And finally rounding off the arrow-head to a smooth point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applied a wash coat of shellac to seal and protect the wood for the rest of the build process and to start to get an idea of how finished product will look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601161647/headstock_2_hu_72ac1a2a230d0c4a.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Headstock with a wash coat of shellac"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure of the tiger maple is starting to pop nicely. This will look nice once it is French polished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601161647/headstock_3_hu_6c49b39d10822335.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Side view of headstock with a wash coat of shellac"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bridge Design</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601141328/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 19:28:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601141328/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I will share some of the decision process used to select the type of bridge used on the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bridge of a multi-scale guitar needs to accommodate the different string lengths, and cannot simply be perpendicular to the strings like on a normal guitar. More specifically, the saddles themselves are not all the same distance from the nut-end of the neck. For this specific guitar, the bridge-end of the strings form a 14 degree angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This requires some special treatment for the builder, since most off-the-shelf bridges will not work. There are a few bridge options that can be purchased, the option of a custom-made bridge, or the option of making my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="midi-guitar"&gt;MIDI Guitar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds another twist to the thought-process. I have been considering making the guitar a MIDI controller as well. I have been looking into the &lt;a href="https://graphtech.com/products/ghost-pickups-strat-tele-2-1-16-spac"&gt;GraphTech Ghost&lt;/a&gt; saddles, which have Piezo transducers embedded within them which allows sending to an acoustic preamp board or a MIDI converter through their &amp;ldquo;Hexpander&amp;rdquo; board. GraphTech has a &lt;a href="https://graphtech.com/collections/ghost-pickup-systems-kits/products/ghost-acousti-phonic-hexpander-preamp"&gt;system of modular components&lt;/a&gt; that work with these saddles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="ghost-saddles"&gt;Ghost Saddles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://graphtech.com/cdn/shop/products/PN-8000-00.jpg?v=1587572523" alt="GraphTech Ghost saddles"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These saddles essentially allow you to send a signal for each individual string. The saddles connect to a circuit board in the guitar (the Hexpander) which outputs to a 13-pin MIDI connector jack. The 13-pin connector from the guitar goes to an external MIDI converter which takes the string signals and outputs midi events which are then sent to a synth. The 13-pin is somewhat of a standard, and there are converter units available such as from Roland, Yamaha, and Axon. (None of this is inexpensive.) I believe this GraphTech system is used in the Parker Fly guitars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="hexpander-kit"&gt;Hexpander Kit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://graphtech.com/cdn/shop/products/pe-0440-00-a.jpg?v=1587572508" alt="GraphTech Hexpander board"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not fully decided on this route, but it would be nice to have this option later and using an appropriate bridge now will make this much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="requirements"&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strat-style saddles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14 degree angle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice-to-haves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slot for Piezo wires (Ghost Saddles)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inexpensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="options"&gt;Options&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hipshot-multi-scale-bridge"&gt;Hipshot Multi Scale Bridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://hipshotproducts.com/cdn/shop/products/4MS06110B.jpg?v=1504663820&amp;amp;width=1280" alt="Hipshot Multi Scale Bridge"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hipshotproducts.com/collections/guitar-bridges/products/6-string-multi-scale-fixed-guitar-bridge"&gt;https://hipshotproducts.com/collections/guitar-bridges/products/6-string-multi-scale-fixed-guitar-bridge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my initial first choice when planning the guitar project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes in 11 degree option which is not exactly the 14 I need, but it would be close enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seems like a solid, well-made bridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low risk of making a bad choice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Somewhat expensive, just over $100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does not have slots for Piezo wires, would need to modify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would require additional cost to upgrade to Ghost saddles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hipshot-solo-bridges"&gt;Hipshot Solo Bridges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://hipshotproducts.com/cdn/shop/products/4S100B.jpg?v=1748958268&amp;amp;width=1280" alt="Hipshot Solo single string bridge"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hipshotproducts.com/collections/guitar-bridges/products/solo-single-string-guitar-bridge"&gt;https://hipshotproducts.com/collections/guitar-bridges/products/solo-single-string-guitar-bridge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these, you buy one for each string and position them individually on the guitar according to the spacing and angle required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be mounted to form any custom angle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built-in slots for Piezo wires&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grooves for height-adjustment screws seems like a nice detail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports top-loaded strings in addition to body-through (cool, although unneeded)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be purchased individually&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expensive. $25 to $30 EACH. (But again, I could by them one-by-one over a few months and spread the cost out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would require additional cost to upgrade to Ghost saddles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think is the best option, barring the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="other-off-the-shelf-options"&gt;Other Off-The-Shelf Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few other multi-scale bridge solutions available to buy. I am ruling them all out due to their cost and other various reasons why I do not like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="abm-single-bridge"&gt;ABM Single Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://abm-guitarpartsshop.com/images/product_images/popup_images/3210b_1.jpg" alt="ABM Single Bridge"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://abm-guitarpartsshop.com/ABM-GUITAR-PARTS/Single-Bridges/Guitar/ABM-3210/ABM-3210b-Black::229.html"&gt;https://abm-guitarpartsshop.com/ABM-GUITAR-PARTS/Single-Bridges/Guitar/ABM-3210/ABM-3210b-Black::229.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="guyker-headless-guitar-bridges"&gt;Guyker Headless Guitar Bridges&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.guyker.com/cdn/shop/files/CNC_Aluminum_Alloy_Headless_Guitar_Bridge_with_Brass_Saddles_Guyker-1.jpg?v=1767773600&amp;amp;width=800" alt="Guyker Headless Guitar bridge"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.guyker.com/products/guyker-wt003-cnc-aluminum-alloy-headless-guitar-bridge-with-brass-saddles"&gt;https://www.guyker.com/products/guyker-wt003-cnc-aluminum-alloy-headless-guitar-bridge-with-brass-saddles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="musiclily"&gt;Musiclily&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81pRab0g1UL._AC_SL1500_.jpg" alt="Musiclily bridges"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Musiclily-Non-tremolo-Individual-Separable-6-Saddle/dp/B0CCS3WG2G"&gt;https://www.amazon.com/Musiclily-Non-tremolo-Individual-Separable-6-Saddle/dp/B0CCS3WG2G&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="diy-bridge"&gt;DIY Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems feasible that I could make my own simple bridge from brass bar/sheet stock. I could color it black using Birchwood-Casey Brass Black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would need to buy the saddles, though, but could get the Ghost saddles right away, or could start with GraphTech string-savers and upgrade to Ghosts later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will be at correct angle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full control of design / can be as simple as needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can use whichever saddles I want without having to &amp;ldquo;buy&amp;rdquo; extra that come with an premade bridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably will not look as clean as a machined bridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More risk in mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potential downside of making unconventional holes/routes into the guitar body that would not be compatible or covered by another type of bridge if I ended up buying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="v1"&gt;V1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my first go at a design. It is basically two pieces. One is a 1/4 inch thick brass bar that the saddles screw into. I am thinking it can be partially embedded into a routed slot in the guitar body. The other piece is a 1/8 thick brass plate for the saddles to rest on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main gist of this design is that the holes for the saddle screws are drilled at the required 14 degree angle, and slightly countersunk on both sides for the screw-head and spring to sit into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601141328/diy-bridge-design_hu_b62d43e3ae3dedc6.jpg" width="796" height="699" alt="Drawing of diy bridge design"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about trying to replicate the design of the HipShot Solo saddles. This seems to require a bend or removing a lot of metal to get the right-angle shape. I am not an metal expert, but believe bending 1/8 thick brass is a no-go unless it is anealed. I am not skilled in this practice so am ruling it out. In short I do not think the HipShot Solo bridge is a feasible design for me to produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="v2"&gt;V2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I soon realized that I could use individual saddle mounts instead of a single solid bar. Some 1/4 inch round brass rod with a hole through the side might work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601141328/diy-bridge-design-2_hu_ed5b0fb2741aaea6.jpg" width="800" height="394" alt="Drawing of diy bridge design, version 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3/8 rod would probably be better. In addition to the hole for the saddle screw, the ends of the hole will need to be drilled wider for the screw head and spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top view showing hole-through, with ends drilled wider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601141328/bridge-post_hu_c241ff5fda0cabf.jpg" width="214" height="178" alt="Drawing of diy bridge post showing hole profile"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that remains now is some brass plate for the height adjustment screws to bear upon. This does not need to be a single piece either. Some small, minimal plates might work, if they could be attached cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="barrel-nuts"&gt;Barrel Nuts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are actually pre-made hardware objects that are almost exactly to this spec. They come in black, too. I have not been able to find the exact size needed though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71tlR5Kg3kL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="Black barrel nuts from Amazon"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mardatt-Barrel-Zinc-Plated-Slotted-Furniture/dp/B0FBFTLKY1"&gt;https://www.amazon.com/Mardatt-Barrel-Zinc-Plated-Slotted-Furniture/dp/B0FBFTLKY1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also seen these nuts in an &amp;ldquo;offset&amp;rdquo; version where the hole is closer to one end, almost just like my design. If I could find these in black, it might be ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I used one of these to attach the mortise-and-tenon neck on my Super K guitar (à la &lt;a href="https://www.cumpiano.com/an-improved-neck-body-joint"&gt;Cumpiano&lt;/a&gt;). These furniture fasteners seem to keep coming up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="custom-made-bridge"&gt;Custom Made Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option is to design my own bridge, or individual parts, but get &lt;a href="https://sendcutsend.com/"&gt;SendCutSend&lt;/a&gt; to make them for me. I have used them before for an acrylic fret spacing template and they provide a great service at very reasonable prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can get the exact design I want&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can use whichever saddles I want without having to buy extra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Requires learning how to 3D-CAD an object (this could be considered a pro actually)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most likely prohibitively expensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tuner Holes</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 21:46:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The tuners have arrived. Now I can finally determine the exact position of the tuners and the holes in the headstock. I like to do this operation with the actual tuners on hand. All bought parts and hardware should be obtained before starting the build, but I could not wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/sperzel_tuners_hu_2430f645335fff4b.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="New set of black Sperzel tuners"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These came directly from Sperzel in Ohio. I really like their locking tuners. I am also a fan of the 12:1 ratio. Most quality tuners are 16:1 or more these days, marketed as being more precise. It is true you can turn them more and get less pitch change which is supposed to make tuning easier. I find that with the high ratio tuners I get annoyed having to turn them so much. I prefer 14:1 or 12:1. They are touchier of course but any guitar player should have no problem using them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also really like their pin-mount system. No screws needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And made in the USA!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/sperzel_tuner_hu_abcdaa33a8a63aed.jpg" width="797" height="600" alt="Sperzel tuner showing mounting pin"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thumbwheel on the back locks the string into the post hole, so no extra wraps are needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, Sperzel is an odd company to do business with. Their tuners are not available from any retail vendor currently, so they must be purchased either from individuals on eBay or Reverb (usually at a markup) or from Sperzel directly. The nice folks at Sperzel do have a website but no online ordering capability or even reliable email correspondence, so orders must be placed by calling them. And then there is no way to check order status or shipment tracking. This is my second time going through this disconcerting process but both times it has worked out great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting the positions of the tuners correct took some careful planning and measuring. I mapped out the positions in Libre Office and printed out a cardstock template which I used to mark the locations of the pilot holes for the tuner posts. Then the pin mount holes were located using a little clear acrylic jig I made that ensures all 6 tuners stay in a line and do not end up looking crooked and out of place. (Jigs specially made just for this purpose can be bought for $30-40 but I like doing things the hard, i.e. cheap, way.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/tuner_holes_template_hu_7ee2cb8abc0d3d87.jpg" width="797" height="600" alt="Positioning the tuner holes with a template"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/tuner_holes_marked_hu_acd9c607218444a4.jpg" width="797" height="600" alt="Marking position of the tuner post holes"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next a #36 drill bit was used to drill the pin mount holes. Then the tuner post holes were drilled out with a 3/8 forstener bit, and reamed ever so slightly to the required 13/32 diameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/tuner_holes_drilled_hu_885c9bb0f6e34ac5.jpg" width="797" height="600" alt="Tuner post and pin holes drilled"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was pretty nerve wracking, though. I was worried I would get something out of line. But with a test-fitting, I think it looks pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/tuners_test_fit_hu_694a7b306d0ef36e.jpg" width="600" height="796" alt="Test fit of the tuners"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601111546/tuners_test_fit_back_hu_e1563ee29329404f.jpg" width="600" height="796" alt="Test fit of the tuners, back view"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I know exactly where the tuning machines will be, the final shape of the headstock can be carved out.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kent Rehab</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 13:41:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/</guid><description>
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_disassembled_hu_5adbcabdd77bef5c.jpg" width="600" height="452" alt="Kent guitar taken apart"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cool 1960s Kent came around again. It is an unusual hollowbody made in Japan, probably by Teisco. This time it was buzzing and ratting around the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to the rattle took some lengthy diagnostics, and I ended up taking it apart to isolate the noise. I believe the rattles and buzzes were possibly coming from multiple sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pickup mounting springs (notorious offenders)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some wood chips, dust, and debris bouncing around inside&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screws and roller wheels in the bridge itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the two bridge-mounting holes. They are NOT placed at the nominal scale-length location but are about a three-eighths of an inch shy, which is weird. More on this to come&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_body_hu_d516ade8b7b179dd.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Kent guitar Body showing bridge holes"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bridges"&gt;Bridges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guitar was found by its owner with a wooden archtop guitar bridge which slid around and was generally useless. Someone put this there probably temporarily to get it semi-playable. Any use of the tremelo would pull the bridge (and loose nut) out way out of alignment. About 10 years ago I replaced it with a metal roller-type bridge, thinking it would work better with the tremelo. This was an improvement, but still not ideal since it was a bit too thick and still did not line up with the mounting holes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the (non)original bridge, and the replacement roller bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_bridges_old_hu_8e53a2d0fdd714c8.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Previous bridges used on the Kent"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new, more vintage-correct and shallower bridge is needed. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="frets"&gt;Frets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from a new bridge, what this guitar really needed was a refret. The first five frets were quite worn and buzzing out. There was some metal left, and I could have tried to simply level and crown these, but the result might have been frets much too low. With consent of the owner, the decision was made go all the way and do a full refret. I happened to have a bunch of 55x110 jumbo fret wire on hand, which should really be a huge improvement in playability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_frets_old_hu_419dfc54f1dbf672.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="Old worn frets"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old frets removed.
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_frets_removed_hu_6f4971f42246b5b8.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="Old frets out"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New frets installed.
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_frets_new_detail_hu_b5f693a2a4100653.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="New frets in"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_frets_installed_hu_d4cc3ef4d299c428.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="Kent guitar neck with new frets"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been practicing the semi-hemispherical fret ends, which are shaped prior to pressing the frets in. I think it makes for a very smooth feel and looks cool, too. No more sharp edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_frets_new_2_hu_66c101d79270fc8a.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="New fret ends"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_frets_new_closeup_hu_81b77f539c96b1b8.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="New fret ends close up"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-bridge"&gt;New Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to eBay, a &amp;ldquo;Vintage Japanese style Super Low Profile Chrome Guitar Bridge&amp;rdquo; can easily be obtained from EZPZ Parts out of Washington state. The metal bushings that came with it are too big for the mounting holes on the guitar, though. Plus putting the bridge directly over the holes would position the bridge too close to the nut and too short for the scale length of the guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will need to fabricate a new base that fits the holes but positions the bridge a bit back from the holes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step 1 is to get the bottom surface contour to match the arched top of the guitar. I have a decent little scrap of rosewood which seems appropriate and fits nicely after some sanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_new_bridge_base_1_hu_15796554f8302d9f.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Making a new base for the new bridge"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_new_bridge_base_2_hu_7fcc52eb3b6b0ea7.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="New bridge base in progress"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reducing the thickness down to where good action will be in range, and adding the mouning posts it is ready for final positioning. I glued some 7/16 dowel pieces to the bottom which fit into the mounting holes, but positioned forward so the intonation point of the bridge is back where it needs to be. The metal screw posts are actually at the far back end of the holes in the guitar body, which is about right in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_new_bridge_base_done_hu_99fbaba8ec4b109d.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="New bridge base mounted"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="scale-length"&gt;Scale Length&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guitar has an odd scale length. It is 640 mm, or 25.19685 inches. My theory is that the guitar was intended to have a 25 or 25.5 inch scale length, and the bridge mounting holes in the body were drilled accordingly. But the fretboard uses a zero-fret, which moves (and shortens in this case) the intonation points. A manufacturing snafu? Who knows. I do like having a zero-fret though, which is common on these Japanese guitars. It makes the action at the nut really easy to get perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New bridge is now in good working order, in the right spot, and stays put. I like this bridge because it is a low profile, and is adjustable both side to side and up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_new_bridge_hu_f698ede926ecbee5.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="New bridge on the guitar"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-nut"&gt;New Nut&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nut itself is not super important on a zero-fret guitar, as the main function is only to control the string spacing. The intonation point and string-height is taken care of the by the zero-fret. However, this old tusq job is looking rough, a bit shallow, and is not quite spaced right anyway. Time for a new bone nut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_nut_new_hu_336da16dcf7e6255.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Making a new nut"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new bone nut shined up and spaced correctly looks way classier.
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_nut_new_done_hu_90e867406b9879d6.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="Detail of the new bone nut on the Kent guitar"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="pickup-mounting"&gt;Pickup Mounting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I replace all pickup mounting springs with lengths of surgical tubing nowadays. This eliminates the buzzing and rattling and general odd vibrations caused by springs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before:
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_pickup_springs_hu_451991834071c169.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Humbucker mounting springs"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After:
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_pickup_tubes_hu_ccf7d9cbac93b871.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Humbucker mounting springs replaced with rubber tubes"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While at it, I also cleaned up some old wiring inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-year-new-life-for-kent"&gt;New Year, New Life for Kent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds and plays great now!
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202601020741/kent_hu_e78dea98c5152311.jpg" width="600" height="797" alt="Kent guitar in all its glory"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Headstock Shaping Part 1</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511181708/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 23:08:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511181708/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Made some progress on the headstock. The edges were cut out on the bandsaw and disk sanded flat. Then the neck &amp;ldquo;flare-outs&amp;rdquo; shaped on the spindle sander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511181708/headstock_spindle_sanding_hu_f7174514a5b2d195.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Shaping the headstock on the spindle sander"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for the fun part - carving the stair-step edge with a paring chisel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511181708/headstock_chiseling_1_hu_de581ac0e17870c2.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Chiseling detail on headstock 1"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511181708/headstock_chiseling_2_hu_cd18214a37132d6c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Chiseling detail on headstock 2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fine, hand-worked details like this are what separate one-off artisan-made guitars from what typically comes from a factory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511181708/headstock_progress_hu_793d8def533fcc32.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="The headstock refined"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still some more to go. The cherry edge on the right needs to be brought in quite a bit to make a smooth point with the other pieces. Then the tip rounded will be rounded off. Overall looking good.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Backstrap</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 22:14:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This was unplanned, but I decided the headstock needed a backstrap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/backstrap_glued_hu_81dbb7432b1ec359.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Backstrap glued into place"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having added the headplate I noticed two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The headstock was too thick by about 1/16 inch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The headstock had a bit more flex than I would prefer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extra thickness could have easily been solved by sanding the backside down. But that would exacerbate the flex problem. I decided to solve both these headstock issues in the following manner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plane off 1/8 of an inch from the back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lay in some carbon fiber reinforcement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a 1/16 thick veneer over the back, extending slightly into the neck area (commonly known as a &amp;ldquo;backstrap&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result will be a headstock that is 1/16 thinner than before but a lot stiffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this meant going back to the Safe-T-Planer to trim down, slicing out another veneer of walnut, and repeating the glue down process used on the headplate. (The backstrap will only be 1 layer thick.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="inlaying-carbon-fiber-bars"&gt;Inlaying Carbon Fiber Bars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backstrap iteself will add a good deal of stiffness, but I figured why not go the extra mile and add in some carbon fiber to make it even stiffer. I happened to have a 4 inch piece leftover from a previous guitar that had a shorter neck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, here is a good methodology. I wish I had figured this out and used this method for the carbon fiber bars I have already glued into the neck. I will know better next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the bar is CA-glued top-down to a sheet of approx 1/8 thick spruce. I had some offcut from an acoustic guitar top that is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/cf_prepare_hu_591b1725c5d042ce.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Carbon Fiber rod glued to spruce stock"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is trimmed out so that the top of the bar has a spruce extension strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/cf_topped_hu_d189f030a6c543d6.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Carbon Fiber rod with spruce on top"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The channel is routed to a depth approx 1/16 deeper than the carbon fiber itself, so that only the spruce extension comes up proud. (The end of this channel is a little sloppy. I really should have done all routing before adding the ears.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/cf_insert_hu_ff747088e46f0ae7.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Carbon Fiber rod ready to install"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now while gluing, the spruce strip on top provides something for the clamps to press on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/cf_gluing_hu_2234d9eb34fcb82a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Carbon Fiber rod glued in"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the extra spruce is planed off, leaving only a nice wood surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/cf_planing_hu_a99566edb128d41a.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Planing off the spruce strip"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/headstock_back_hu_f23d9fe3597b37d8.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Back of headstock ready for backstrap"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is ideal because the carbon fiber is protected from being scaped, planed, or sanded now. It should not be cut or worked at all, really, for safety reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="backstrap-installed"&gt;Backstrap Installed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now with the backstrap glued down, the headstock is the perfect 9/16 thick and it feels MUCH stiffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I have traced the outline of the headstock template upside down to show approximately where the cutout will be. Note the rounded area where the headstock meets the neck. This little rounded section will extend into the neck just past the 0-fret line. Much of this end will be trimmed off and shaped during neck-carving, but I wanted to get that rounded part pre-shaped at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511171614/backstrap_outline_hu_100eb57f84638d90.jpg" width="602" height="800" alt="Back of headstock showing outline"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOW the headstock is ready to be trimmed out.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wiring Diagram</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511161921/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 01:21:41 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511161921/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a drawing of the planned wiring scheme. This is not a true schematic, but a simple diagram of the components and their connections. At this point the emphasis is on the switches to make sure the functionality I want will be possible. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also not laid out according to where the components will be on the guitar yet. It is just to get an idea of the circuit and the connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511161921/wiring_hu_ff8a442904962cfe.jpg" width="1440" height="731" alt="proposed wiring diagram"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the 2-pole on/on switches, the vertical gray bars represent the connections that get made when switch is thrown. They are shown in the above diagram in the &amp;ldquo;Down&amp;rdquo; position, where the connections are from lugs 5 to 6 and 2 to 3. When in the &amp;ldquo;Up&amp;rdquo; position the connections are 5-4 and 1-2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The on/off/on toggle is going to be interesting. I am planning on using a standard three-position toggle switch like in a Gibson two-pickup guitar. These switches are actually on/on/on, and the middle position will place the two pickups in parallel. I really want these in series, though. So I may need to use a different kind of switch, or possibly modify the Gibson-type to be on/off/on. Apparently this is possible with the Switchcraft switches which can be taken apart (since they are assembled with screws) and put back together as on/off/on by flipping the contacts around.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Headplate</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:14:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The headplate on this guitar will be 1/8 inch thick made up of two layers of 1/16 inch veneers - walnut with curly-maple on top. The first step is to slice out the veneers. The curly-maple is from the same board as the body of the guitar (recall the extra third section that was fortunately not needed) so should match nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-veneers-rough_hu_e682b4de1b4bca19.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Rough cut veneer sheets for the headstock"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thickness-sanding"&gt;Thickness Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next they are sanded close to their final thickness on the spindle sander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are approximately 3/16 inch thick now but need to be 1/16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/thinning-before_hu_ef512e66b072d742.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Before thinning"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/spindle-sander_hu_e1c4e689ddc061fe.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Thinning veneer on the spindle sander"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will stop at around .070 or just a bit more than 1/16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/thinning-after_hu_43044cee70761e64.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="After thinning"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thickness comes after some more sanding with a random orbit sander, and then hand sanding. To make this easier, I use double-sided tape to hold them down to a board that is clamped to the bench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/sanding_hu_7be896e9efd3a9ed.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Hand sanding to final thickness"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After sanding, they total about 1/8 of an inch which is the target thickness of the headplate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/post-sanding_hu_a9fe9e83554f291f.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Veneer pair sanded to overall final thickness"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bending"&gt;Bending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this guitar has a radiused end where the fretboard meets the headstock (Fender style) the headplate will be bent to accommodate this curve. The plates, even though only 1/16 inch thick, are not this flexible at all so will need to be heat-bent to shape first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is done by wetting the veneer with water and then bending over a hot pipe (around 350-400 degrees) to the necessary curve . Then they are held down to where they need to go to dry and cool using the spindle as a mold. This is basically the same way I bend hollowbody guitar sides, which I can hopefully cover in more detail in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/bending-drying_hu_18bf317ea4043ff5.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Headstock veneers cooling in the mold after bending"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now they are thicknessed and bent and ready to glue down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplates-pre-glue_hu_ca0679b4911ce9d5.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Headstock veneers bent and ready to be attached"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gluing"&gt;Gluing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once correctly positioned, I use two small drill bits as index-pins in the waste areas to lock down the location and keep it from sliding around during gluing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-alignment_hu_bcebbe24d66d0558.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Headplate veneer positioned and indexed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special top and bottom cauls and multiple clamps to apply pressure. Again, hot hide glue is used for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-gluing_hu_73b2e2ae8bcd5f4b.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Gluing down a headplate veneer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The walnut layer glued down first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/walnut-layer-glued_hu_96f274bb6a4c41c.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Walnut veneer glued"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then then maple layer glued on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/maple-layer-glued_hu_66e9e47be125def3.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Maple veneer glued"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="clean-up-and-trim"&gt;Clean up and trim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wrap up this stage, the overhang where the fretboard meets the headstock is trimmed back flush to the neck. This trimmed end will be covered by the end of the fretboard when it is attached later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headplate-trimmed_hu_babfe9ad897f5e01.jpg" width="800" height="602" alt="Trimming end of headplate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can see how the final shape of the headstock will be cut out (note light pencil lines) and where the holes for the tuners will go. I might make some final adjustments here, but this is pretty close to the final shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511151814/headstock-outlined_hu_dafc4619a78dea51.jpg" width="452" height="600" alt="Outline of headstock"&gt;</description></item><item><title>Electronics Plan V1</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511100736/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:36:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511100736/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some cold weather today so I am staying out of the shop and taking a closer look at the electronics planned for the guitar. Once the guitar is fully assembled and strung up for the first time (before finishing, though) I will see what it sounds like and test out different circuits and components using an external breadboard before drilling the final holes for the potentiometers (pots) and switches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="initial-idea"&gt;Initial Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/202511100736/electronics-layout-800_hu_fef085444fcc2d45.jpg" width="800" height="772" alt="initial idea for electronics"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pickup-selector-toggle"&gt;Pickup Selector Toggle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a Les Paul style &lt;a href="https://www.stewmac.com/electronics/components-and-parts/switches/axlabs-3-way-6-pole-toggle-switch/"&gt;three-position toggle&lt;/a&gt; for the neck pickup, bridge pickup, or both in parallel. Black. I considered other options such as individual on/off switches for each pickup or a Telecaster-style blade pickup, but landed on the toggle with the idea that it is the most fool-proof way to easily flip while playing. The exact placement will be determined once I actually try to play the guitar to see where my hand goes when moving my elbow to get it in just the right spot. I will also angle switch movement so as not to make it &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; easy to flip to avoid accidentally switching it during vigorous strumming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck-and-bridge-tap-switches"&gt;Neck and Bridge Tap Switches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These will be &lt;a href="https://lovemyswitches.com/taiway-dpdt-on-on-switch-solder-lug-short-shaft-black-plated/"&gt;mini on/on toggle switches&lt;/a&gt; to control the pickup taps. The plan is to use &lt;a href="https://www.seymourduncan.com/single-product/quarter-pound-strat"&gt;Seymour Duncan Quarter Pound Strat&lt;/a&gt; Tapped pickups, which have a normal, modern high-output lead plus an additional tapped lead for a more vintage half-power output. This will allow the player to get two different sounds out of each pickup. I expect the normal (up) position will be more suitable for modern high-gain styles and the tapped (down) will produce more a traditional clean/jangly strat-type sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tone-bypass"&gt;Tone ByPass&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mini on/on toggle that will allow bypassing the tone circuit completely. When down, the normal tone and volume signal path is active. When switched up, the tone controls are bypassed and have no effect, so only the volume control is in the circuit. The thinking is that tone controls do attenuate the signal even when turned all the way up, because the resistance of the pots is not infinite and some signal is still getting grounded. Add in the capacitors, and there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; tone being changed even when the tone is on &amp;ldquo;10&amp;rdquo;. So this allows the player to get an even more pure and raw signal from the pickups without any influence by the tone controls. Only the volume control still works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tone-knob-1---bass-cut"&gt;Tone Knob 1 - Bass Cut&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit different from a normal single-tone control on a guitar. This guitar will have separate treble and bass controls (passive). This is directly copying the G&amp;amp;L S500 wiring. Most guitars just have a single tone control which attenuates the high frequencies. Here with the additional bass-frequency attenuation, the player will be able to clean up the signal to cut through a mix better by cutting out some bass. This will be a 1MG Ohm audio taper pot, with a small capacitor around 1000 picofarads. When testing the circuit I will determine the best capacitor value. Black, &lt;a href="https://lovemyswitches.com/anodized-aluminum-knob-the-hi-fi-1-4-smooth-shaft-20mm-od/"&gt;20mm aluminum knobs&lt;/a&gt; for the tone controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tone-knob-2---treble-cut"&gt;Tone Knob 2 - Treble Cut&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the more traditional tone control that just cuts the high end. I am thinking 500k audio-taper pot, with a .022 microfarad capacitor. Again, will experiment to find a good sounding capacitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="volume"&gt;Volume&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic volume control. 250k linear pot. I prefer linear pots for volume, as opposed to audio-taper. Note the large knob&amp;hellip; I am thinking of using &lt;a href="https://lovemyswitches.com/solid-aluminum-knob-mission-control-1-4-smooth-shaft-32mm-od/"&gt;freakishly large 32mm knob&lt;/a&gt; for the volume to allow the player to easily grab it with their pinky finger while playing to do dramatic volume swells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="direct-out"&gt;Direct Out&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last on/on toggle switch near the volume, which will bypass both the volume and tone from the circuit and send the pickup signal directly to the jack. This is for an even more pure, raw signal unaffected by any pots or capacitors. This can act as a mini &amp;ldquo;boost&amp;rdquo; effect during a performance. Used this way, it is sometimes called a blower switch. It might also be useful for recording, where all tone and volume is controlled during mixing and you want the purest and loudest signal to be recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="jack"&gt;Jack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thinking of trying one of these &lt;a href="https://www.amplifiedparts.com/products/jack-pure-tone-mono-open-circuit"&gt;PureTone&lt;/a&gt; jacks. In black of course to match all the other hardware. The jack will be in the side of guitar, Telecaster style, using a nice &lt;a href="https://www.stewmac.com/parts-and-hardware/jack-plates/electrosocket-jack-mount/"&gt;recessed plate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="breadboarding"&gt;Breadboarding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I usually do is mount the pickups into the guitar and connect the leads to a breadboard tester on my desk, which is then connected to an amp. The allows me to fiddle around with different components and wiring schemes before soldering anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More photos and updates to come on this subject.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>