<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Electric Guitar Build 2025-2026 on DAEBFCG</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/series/electric-guitar-build-2025-2026/</link><description>Recent content in Electric Guitar Build 2025-2026 on DAEBFCG</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 21:39:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://daebfcg.github.io/series/electric-guitar-build-2025-2026/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Initial Conception and Design</title><link>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 21:39:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="new-solid-body-electric-guitar-project"&gt;New solid-body electric guitar project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my next guitar project I&amp;rsquo;ll be building a solid-body electric guitar from scratch. The inspiration for the design comes partly from the Alembic Further guitar with a neck-through design and curly maple top and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m building off this basic Strat type guitar design with a couple of customizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://daebfcg.github.io/posts/20251010/ElectricGuitar_hu_33e04fe05c90dec6.png" width="261" height="800" alt="Plans"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="multi-scale"&gt;Multi Scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost is the multi-scale. It will be 25.5&amp;quot; on the bass side, and 25&amp;quot; on the treble. This is to retain the rich overtones on the bass notes (i.e. more Fenderish twang), while fattening up the high end with a little less overtone and more fundamental (i.e. getting in to Les Paul territory, but not quite.) The 25.5&amp;quot; is typical Fender strat, and the 25 is used on PRS and Danelectro guitars. I could have gone shorter on the treble to get even more fatter/sweeter sound there, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been liking the feel of the slightly longer scale lengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="neck-through"&gt;Neck Through&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always said if I build a solid body, it will be a neck through. It just seems to make sense structurally for good sound coupling. Hopefully it will give it some extra sustain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="two-pickups"&gt;Two Pickups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; pickup. The plan is to use 2 Seymour Duncan Quarter Pound Strat pickups, mounted directly to the body. No pickguard. (More detail on the electronics coming up later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="body-shape"&gt;Body Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is based loosely on a strat, but is more in the 80&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;super strat&amp;rdquo; vein with sharper horns. I&amp;rsquo;ve also narrowed the mid-section a bit, inspired by the early 70&amp;rsquo;s Kay strat knockoff guitars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="chambered-body"&gt;Chambered Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it won&amp;rsquo;t actually be a fully solid body. To cut down on weight, as well as give some extra airy resonance, The body will have 2 large empty chambers. The chamber on the right side will conveniently house the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="plans"&gt;Plans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all my guitar builds, I first start with a full-size drawing using Libre Office Draw. From this, I print out cardstock templates.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>